Guide to the Maurine Watkins Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Maurine Watkins papers
1890-2012
YCAL MSS 1079
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.75
7 boxes
The Maurine Watkins Papers, which span from 1890 to 2012, contain writings, including scripts and short stories, printed material, correspondence, photographs and other papers by or relating to Maurine Watkins. Watkins was a journalist and playwright whose most well-known work was the play "Chicago," which Bob Fosse adapted into an award-winning musical.
Watkins, Maurine
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Ken Lopez Bookseller, Ann Margaret Brown Buckland and Peter L. Brown on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, and the Adele Gutman Nathan Theaterical Collection Fund, 2016.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Plays, 1926-2012. II. Other Writings, 1927-1949. III. Personal Papers, 1890-1939.
Maurine Watkins
Maurine Dallas Watkins (1896-1969) was a playwright and journalist most well-known for writing the play "Chicago." Watkins was born in Kentucky, attended several colleges including Radcliffe College, and got hired by the Chicago Tribune as a reporter in 1924. While working at the Tribune, Watkins reported on the trials of Beulah Annan and Belva Gaertner, who were both found not guilty of murder. Soon after, Watkins left her position at the Tribune and went to Yale University to continue her studies, eventually writing a fictionalized version of the Annan and Gaertner trials entitled "Chicago." Watkins went on to write over twenty plays. After Watkins's death of lung cancer, her estate sold the rights of 'Chicago" to Bob Fosse, who adapted the play into a successful musical.
Scope and Contents
The Maurine Watkins Papers, which span from 1890 to 2012, contain writings, including scripts and short stories, printed material, correspondence, photographs and other papers by or relating to Maurine Watkins. Watkins was a journalist and playwright whose most well-known work was the play "Chicago," which Bob Fosse adapted into an award-winning musical.
American drama -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Dramatists, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographs; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Dramatists -- United States -- 20th Century; Watkins, Maurine; Ken Lopez Bookseller; Buckland, Ann Margaret Brown; Brown, Peter L.
- Plays, 1926-2012; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Materials arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  Primarily contains plays written by Maurine Watkins including manuscript drafts and typescripts, along with a small number of photographs and pieces of ephemera.
  - Against the day, undated (Box 1)
  - An old fashioned girl, undated (Box 1)
  - Blue roses, undated (Box 1)
  - Chicago, undated (Box 1)
  - Chicago, undated (Box 1)
  - Chicago, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Chicago: printed version, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Chicago: printed version (in German), 1927 (Box 1)
  - Chicago 1975, undated (Box 1)
  - Chicago: photographs, undated (Box 2)
  - Photos, articles, and the "Chicago" file 2009, undated (Box 2)
  - Gesture, undated (Box 2)
  - Gesture, undated (Box 2)
  - Glory, undated (Box 2)
  - Henrietta's mother, undated (Box 2)
  - Legend, undated (Box 2)
  - Mardi Gras or Snatch the city, undated (Box 2)
  - Mardi Gras, undated (Box 2)
  - Marshland, undated (Box 2)
  - Marshland, undated (Box 2)
  - Marshland, undated (Box 3)
  - Marshland, undated (Box 3)
  - Prologue, undated (Box 3)
  - Quick action, undated (Box 3)
  - Real Jan Braaten, undated (Box 3)
  - Real Jan Braaten, undated (Box 3)
  - Revelry, undated (Box 3)
  - Rivers of Babylon, undated (Box 3)
  - Snatch the day!, undated (Box 3)
  - Snatch the day!, undated (Box 3)
  - Snatch the day!, undated (Box 3)
  - So help me God!, undated (Box 4)
  - So help me God!, undated (Box 4)
  - So help me God!, undated (Box 4)
  - So help me God!, undated (Box 4)
  - So help me God!, undated (Box 4)
  - So help me God!: program, 2009-12 (Box 4)
  - Tinsel girl, undated (Box 4)
  - Tinsel girl, undated (Box 4)
  - Velvet, undated (Box 4)
  - Program for "Up the River", 1930-10-10 (Box 4)
  - Young must live, undated (Box 4)
- Other writings, 1927-1949; Series II; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Contains writings by Maurine Watkins including short stories, personal notes, and writings from her time in school.
  - Alimony, undated (Box 5)
  - All out for love, undated (Box 5)
  - All out for love, undated (Box 5)
  - Blue flower, undated (Box 5)
  - Blue flower, undated (Box 5)
  - Blue flower, 1949-06 (Box 5)
  - Bound, undated (Box 5)
  - Bound, undated (Box 5)
  - Bound, undated (Box 5)
  - Bound, undated (Box 5)
  - Butterfly goes home, undated (Box 5)
  - Change, undated (Box 5)
  - Circus story, undated (Box 5)
  - Doors, undated (Box 5)
  - Home free, undated (Box 5)
  - Honors are even, undated (Box 5)
  - Leaf from Eve, undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous short stories, 1927-1928 (Box 5)
  - Morning glory, undated (Box 5)
  - Notes on art, inc., undated (Box 5)
  - Poison, undated (Box 5)
  - Poison, undated (Box 5)
  - Same boat, undated (Box 5)
  - Thistle, undated (Box 5)
  - Thistle, undated (Box 5)
  - Wait, colonel, undated (Box 6)
  - World wise, undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous short stories, undated (Box 6)
  - School writings, undated (Box 6)
  - Bible college writings, undated (Box 6)
  - Bible college writings, undated (Box 6)
- Personal papers, 1890-1939; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  Materials within this series are organized maintain the original physical organization found at time of acquisition.
  Contains materials related to Maurine Watkins' personal life.
  - Correspondence, 1920-1939 (Box 7)
  - Estate records, undated (Box 7)
  - Hamburg trip itinerary, no year, August (Box 7)
  - Passport, 1933 (Box 7)
  - George Watkins theological notes, 1890-09 (Box 7)
  - Photograph, undated (Box 7)